Charts with trends is a type of chart
that shows changes over time of different subjects.
Meanwhile, charts of comparison do not show trends
or changes over time, but only show comparisons between the subjects.
Hey there, it's me.
Do you realise that the start of today's lesson  is a bit weird?
Suddenly, the teacher just started talking a lot,
no beginning, no end, no idea what the lesson was.
If our paragraph doesn't have a topic sentence,
we'll have the same problem.
And the examiners cannot follow it because
they don't know what the main idea of the paragraph is.
So today, we're learning about topic sentences.
Our lesson is divided into two parts.
Part one, the topic sentence, definition and features.
And part two, practice, to achieve two goals.
Help you remember and understand the features of topic sentences,
and apply this knowledge to identify effective topic sentences.
I won't keep you guys waiting much longer,
let's get right into it.
If you want to learn something, you need to know what it is first, right?
So let's discuss the definition of the topic sentence
through a mini-task.
Please read the paragraph below and answer
two following questions in one minute.
So are you ready?
Let's do it.
With the first question, choose the best title for the paragraph, we can see that
the whole paragraph focuses on reasons why people play musical instruments.
Specifically, the first reason is that
some opt to learn an instrument for the purpose of
The second reason is it serves as their hobby.
So the best title for this paragraph is
B, motivations behind playing a musical instrument.
And within the three options of question two,
sentence A, there are several reasons why people
choose to play a musical instrument,  best expresses the main idea in the title of the paragraph,
while B and C are just two details in the paragraph to clarify sentence A.
So A is the topic sentence of this paragraph.
From this example, can you guess what features a topic sentence has?
In 30 seconds, please choose all the correct answers to this question.
Your time starts now.
From the sample paragraph at the beginning of today's lesson,
we can see that a topic sentence carries the main idea of the whole
paragraph and other sentences will support, explain or illustrate the topic sentence.
Remember, all information in the paragraph must be
related to the topic sentence, so we cannot have  one or two unrelated or off-topic
sentences in the paragraph.
And certainly, you must write this sentence very clearly,
but not imply something and then hope that the examiner will read and understand it on their own.
Don't challenge the examiner to do matching headings.
A topic sentence only presents the main idea
of the paragraph without explaining it.
Correct!
The topic sentence only summarizes the main idea
of the paragraph, so it should not be
wordy or lengthy.
Explaining is the function of the following sentences.
Also, from the previous lesson, the most effective
way of writing paragraphs in IELTS writing test
2 is the deductive method, so G is a correct answer.
A topic sentence is usually placed at the
beginning of the paragraph, not anywhere in the paragraph.
And because it's a topic sentence, not sentences,
we only write it once in the paragraph,
rather than repeating it many times.
Alright, so we've just learned about the definition
and features of a topic sentence.
Now, let's move on to the components of
a good topic sentence.
A topic sentence is composed of two parts.
In a topic sentence, there must be a topic,
or the subject we need to discuss.
For example, in this sentence we have,  play a musical instrument as the topic.
From this, we know the main idea of the whole paragraph.
In addition, an effective topic sentence also
needs to have a controlling idea to show which
aspect of the topic will be developed in the paragraph.
Without this part, the sentence would only have
the topic, people choose to play a musical instrument.
This will make readers confused about which aspect
of playing a musical instrument will be discussed.
It could be advantages and disadvantages, or results
of playing a musical instrument, or how often people play it.
Thanks to the controlling idea, several reasons, the
readers know that in this paragraph we will
focus on the reasons why people play musical instruments.
From here, we have the structure of a
topic sentence as follows.
Now let's have a try with a small task.
I'll give you a topic sentence and you
will identify the two components of it within
15 seconds.
Ready?
Set?
Go!
Ah yes, it's still the topic we've just discussed,
playing a musical instrument.
But now it's not about the reasons why
people play musical instruments anymore, but a number
of challenges, and this is the controlling idea of the topic sentence.
So the readers will know that this paragraph
is about some disadvantages of playing a musical
instrument, but not other aspects.
Let's do another one, 15 seconds for you.
Similarly, music is the topic.
To discuss music, there are many things we
can talk about, but the controlling idea has
narrowed down the topic to various health benefits,
so the paragraph will only focus on some health benefits of music.
Different types of essays in IELTS in particular,
and in English in general, have their own
effective ways of writing a topic sentence.
We'll learn about them later in the course.
For now, just make sure to clearly understand
this type of sentence so that we can use it easily in the future.
Alright, let's practice a bit now.
Let's go!
Now, I will give you a paragraph that
is missing a topic sentence.
Your task is to read this paragraph and
choose the most suitable topic sentence for it
within 90 seconds.
Let's start.
If you're not careful, you might choose option A
but it's incorrect, because the paragraph does
not discuss health benefits of music.
You might say, the idea, enhance our mood
and reduce stress, is related to health.
However, it just talks about our emotions, not
the overall health.
Even if it's about health, this is just
one idea in the whole paragraph.
And we also have another idea, fosters our communication skills, right?
So option A is not the title of the paragraph.
Let's analyse option D.
Music and emotion are closely connected.
This seems relevant to this paragraph, right?
However, again, this is just one idea in this paragraph.
So this option cannot be the topic sentence of the paragraph.
As we've learned, all information in the paragraph
must be related to the topic sentence.
In other words, the topic sentence must summarise
all ideas in the paragraph.
So D is incorrect.
We're going to move on to option B.
Music is fantastic.
This sentence is too general, because it doesn't
show which aspect of music will be discussed.
It can talk about the beauty, the benefits of music, or simply the feelings of the writer.
So this is not the topic sentence for the paragraph.
The correct answer is C.
There are numerous benefits that music can bring.
This sentence summarises both the ideas, enhance our
mood and reduce stress, and fosters our communication skills.
We will learn the structures to write
an effective topic sentence like this later in the course, guys.
Let's look at the whole paragraph again, and
everyone, please pause the video and write down
this paragraph in your notebook or type it out.
Remember to follow five features of an English
paragraph that we learned in the previous lesson,
and especially highlight the topic sentence so we can learn from it.
I'll wait for you in the wrap-up section.
Alright, we've just learned about the topic sentence,
which is considered as an important foundation for next lessons.
Together, we have achieved the goals.
Remember and understand features of topic sentences.
And apply this knowledge to identify effective topic sentences.
See you in the next lesson.
I'm Anna.
Goodbye and see you next time.